[Music]
thank you
hello good evening good day and welcome
to the ask Abhijit show where I take
questions from you and I answer those
questions so to those of you who are new
to the channel welcome and thank you for
joining for those of you who are regular
viewers welcome back thank you for
joining and for those of you who don't
know how to ask questions you can ask me
questions in the comments in any of the
videos on my channel and use the hashtag
ask a budget so that I can find your
question that's how you ask your
questions right with that said let's see
who all is there on the live chat I can
see Radha upte lone Rider Vishal Natha
jatin Gupta Payne Sunita Supra
nilab Akash dobreal Tango Charlie Gupta
Twilight Sumit Agarwal Appleseed
Mahendra Miguel Diaz kushirani Reeves
foreign
and lots and lots and lots of other
people so nice to have you all on this
live chat I'm unfortunate I cannot greet
you all by name but thank you so much
for being on this Krabby feet uh so not
I'll take some more names proful Jay
Patel Lord Arjun vinayak
and uh everybody else everybody else
and everybody else so with that uh with
that done let's take some questions
right let's uh I can see lots of people
saying hello hello to you all hello to
you all all right all right let's get
into the into the heart of the matter
let's take some questions what's
question number one what is question
number one
okay I don't really know how to read
Bengali so I'll just go into question I
would like to understand why only the
Tigers of the sundarbans are
traditionally man eaters
there there are many folklores like due
to the salty water they drink Etc but I
haven't seen any scientific report
anywhere well I'm not sure that the
Tigers of the sundarbans region drink
salty water from that is not something
that um that mammals or animals do I
mean salt water mammals would probably
swallow salty water or not like whales
and maybe crocodiles which are not
mammals to do that but uh
so let's let's see where is the where is
the sundarban's region yes let's see
where that is let's go to the maps yes
today we are starting with the map where
is the sundarbans
so we go to the East part of India
eastern part of India it's
it's in the uh Delta region of uh
unified Bengal Bangladesh yeah which is
mainly Bangladesh and also parts of
Indian Bengal yeah
so we have the great Padma River or the
ganga which grains into uh the the Sea
of Kalinga or the Bay of Bengal whatever
you want to call it Indian Ocean and
there are various other tributaries lots
of rivers that also drain into this
region and this entire region is full of
these Mangrove forests and other forests
that's called the sundarbans right
uh and yes this is this region is a home
to a whole lot of tigers I'm not sure
it's a very large tiger population but
yeah one of the largest tiger
populations that still survives in the
world yeah and yes these tigers have
this um reputation of of uh hunting
people yeah of killing people that's why
they're called man eaters so why is this
why is it that these tigers do that why
do they have this reputation of being
managers first of all this is a highly
populated area uh Bangladesh and Bengal
have some of the highest population
densities in the world and lots of
people live in the sundarbans people
um rely on the sundarban's forests
forests for uh a variety of purposes for
the livelihood for Gathering honey for
fishing for other things yeah so they
venture out into the forest or sometimes
in small groups sometimes alone yeah so
they prove they they present a very
tempting opportunity for these large
cats you know for for a very for a cheap
meal typically a tiger has to work
really hard for his or her meal to hunt
animals and animals are really well
adapted to trying to to evade tigers so
it's really hard work to get a decent
meal when you have this slow moving
ape-like creatures human beings who
can't really run and who can't see in
the dark it's kind of really easy for a
tiger to catch people such such prey
and typically Tigers uh don't do this
but once a tiger gets the taste of this
and he or she realizes how easy it is to
just hunt humans then they start doing
that and once so I mean tigers are
typically solitary cats they don't live
in large social groups but yes one or
two of them they learn this and maybe
others would pick up pick it up from
them especially if it's a mother who's
teaching her kids her Cubs how to hunt
yeah and then that may be passed on from
generation to generation that sort of
thing may happen yeah so that's the
reason why there are lots of these these
scary stories of man eating tigers in
the sundarbans region in in Bengal in
unified Bengal in overall the Bengal
region yeah I'm not sure I don't think
all of the Tigers there are managers but
yes human beings present a very tempting
meal for tigers and it's easy to hunt
humans uh so so and because of the high
population density and all that that's
why it's likely that this phenomenon
occurs there but it's not like only the
time Tigers of the sunderbans have been
monitors we have had reports of of
magnetic Tigers throughout the ages in
India I mean even during the British
occupation of India uh you had the the
so-called Corbett National Park we still
have this National Park which is called
the Jim Corbett National Park Jim
Corbett was a poacher he was a murderer
of animals and he was a foreign occupier
but we have named this natural park
after this fellow Jim Corbett who is
known for killing tigers
so during the time of Jim Corbett when
he was alive and he was yeah well he was
there in Northern India uh there were
many reports of various tigers that had
taken to to killing human beings yeah
so when he he personally took out some
of some of these Tigers this fellow Jim
Corbett so there are report there are
reports from that region of tigers
turning to uh killing human beings there
are reports of other animals also
turning to killing human beings like
leopards in for instance in in Western
India in Mumbai there is this National
Park I don't know what it's called it's
some strange name uh there is a
structural Park in Mumbai where there
you have the largest I mean the highest
population density of leopards probably
in the world and these leopards
sometimes you know they prey on humans
once in a while because uh well it's
easy yeah humans are the slowest of the
creatures they can hunt typically they
go after goats and dogs and all that and
uh sometimes deer also in other small
animals but sometimes human beings and
uh so that's what happens in it's not
just leopards in in Tigers uh I I
remember many many years ago when I was
a kid I watched this movie when I was a
teenager or something I watched a movie
called The Ghost in the darkness uh it
was a movie set in Kenya at the turn of
the 19th century 19 20th century late
19th century and uh it's about the
construction of a railroad in Kenya and
Indian origin workers are involved I
think om Puri was one of the actors yeah
so this movie The Ghost of The Ghost and
the Darkness was about the this these
two animals these two lions these two
lions were siblings brothers and they
were called The Man Eaters of Savo so
these lines also it seems like they
exclusively hunted human beings because
it was so easy to catch to hunt humans
so this is a phenomenon you see across
the world
wherever you have big cats once a big
cat whether it's a lion or a tiger or
any other large cat once he or she
realizes that it's that you can hunt
humans and how easy it is then they kind
of you know get lazy and they go on
doing that because it makes sense you
know less energy expenditure and almost
like a guaranteed meal
so that's why large cats take two
occasionally take two hunting human
beings so it's not like it's something
that's exclusive to the Tigers of the
sundarbans it's not like it's exclusive
to only Tigers I think lots of animals
do this even Bears typically they don't
hurt humans but there have been reports
of bears whether it is polar bears or
those brown bears the Klondike bears in
Alaska or various other parts of of uh
of the of the of North America even
bears in India sometimes you hear about
bears attacking humans yeah but
typically it's when humans provoke them
so that's how it goes it's not like the
Tigers of sundarbans are exclusively
managers or traditionally managers it's
just that it's happened because of the
overpopulation of the region the Tigers
shrinking habitat and the paucity of uh
prey that they have resources to hunt
and that's why they sometimes take to uh
to hunting or preying upon human beings
but it's not something that's exclusive
to these Tigers all right I hope that
answers this question great question to
start off with what else do we have
SRI Ram kannan says I am from Singapore
the other day I was discussing with my
school Professor about the rise of
Singapore he said that Singapore had an
Iron Man called Lee Kuan Yew who had
harmonized Singapore again under one
umbrella which had unified Singapore he
also said that colonialism in Singapore
was a good thing that had brought
English which unified everyone under one
language
he says why can't India do the same
India should be unified under one
language as well I said that's not
possible because of the cultural
diversity in evolution I would like to
know your views on this matter do you
think India could ever be unified wholly
under a language despite having a lot of
diversity India has always had a huge
amount of diversity going back to Vedic
times it's not like in during The Vedic
times when was written there was only
one language
there must have been lots of languages
spoken even then but we have always had
one unifying civilizational language so
people in various parts of India they
would have speak and spoken various
languages but these languages are all in
some way or the other interconnected
interrelated and and uh in some way
alike and the common language that that
uh unified everything was Sanskrit that
was always the linked language the
civilization language that's the
language that's spread across Eurasia
yeah and so that's how it is now coming
to Lee Kuan Yew Lee Kuan Yew is a very
interesting person uh clearly the great
uh the Grand Master of Singapore the
great DD fire of Singapore he was first
elected prime minister I believe in 1959
yeah 1959 so where is Singapore let's go
to the map once again where is the map
Singapore so we know where India is
let's go south south south and we know
where Malaysia is yes the Malacca State
we all know I believe because you watch
my channel you know where the Malacca
Strait is so at the other end of the
Malacca Strait you have this island city
called Singapore it's Singapore it's a
Sanskrit name
and you can see it's at the southern tip
of Malaysia of course you have another
part of Malaysia on this island here
kaliman yep Borneo or whatever so
Singapore so uh there was a time when
Singapore was unified with Malaysia and
then there were various issues in this
the singaporeans uh I think they left
Malaysia there was this partition or
whatever you want to call it secession
of Singapore from Malaysia in the early
1960s what what year was it 63 65
somewhere around there look it up okay I
don't memorize dates uh and Lee Kuan Yew
was the prime minister of Singapore he
was
first elected 59 most likely then he or
was the prime minister of Singapore
essentially the dictator of Singapore
you could say from 1965 to I think 1990
in even after 1990 he was the most
powerful politician but he did not have
any official position after 1990 which
actually is more suitable to being in in
in power you know no responsibilities
and and a lot of power so think what Lee
Kuan do you did is that he took
Singapore out of within a generation
within let's say 20 years from the
status of a third world country to a
highly prosperous highly developed first
world nation with one of the highest
rates of per capita GDP and one of the
most amazing levels of prosperity
anywhere in the world he did this within
a generation within 20 years so 1960s
Singapore is a third world nation with
slums and and and broken down system and
no infrastructure Nothing by the 1980s
it is a highly prosperous first world
country very highly developed huge
booming economy
excellent Prosperity so Lee Kuan Yew uh
was a firm believer in the English
language yeah uh of course he did recent
colonialism to a certain extent but he
was kind of an anglo-file he uh
he reformed Singapore he instituted this
very strong one-party system essentially
essentially a one-party system
essentially a dictatorship with a very
strong focus on the economy with a very
strong strong focus on social harmony
Singapore is is a is a city that's a
Melting Pot of Indians and Indians and
and Chinese mainly you know malays also
the three main ethnicities yeah so he
harmonized them under this umbrella of
English yeah social harmony Economic
Development education very strong and
very rigorous education for everybody
and and public housing all these things
yeah so he did a superb job a stupendous
job of doing this and the Chinese have
tried to copy this so Lee Kuan Yew was a
ethnic Chinese person so the Chinese
Communist Party send lots of officials
to Singapore to study the methods of
Singapore and I think Deng Xiaoping used
to say that if I have to transform
Shanghai into Singapore I can do it in a
decade but China is so enormous it's a
huge struggle so the same thing applies
to India as well it's very easy to
transform a city-state which is just one
city the smaller the system the more
complex can be your adjustments but the
larger the system
the simpler you have to keep things the
policies and all that so so Lee Kuan you
had this wonderful set of policies that
really worked it totally transformed
Singapore of course there are complaints
about Authority authoritarianism about
the imposed uni you know you uh unifying
foreign language and all those things
it's it's very harsh the rule is very
harsh the fines are very hard and the
discipline is very harsh and all that
but overall it's been it's worked out
really great for the people of Singapore
uh so the question is what about India
so so leak one you came to India a few
times he was actually you could say um
he was fond of India I mean if you read
his books I have a couple of those books
lying around somewhere uh he writes
about India and he he speaks about the
caste system that the caste system and
all that is going to keep India back and
he recounts he recollects that he had
visited India New Delhi and he remembers
how shoddy the rashtrapati Bhavan was
and uh he's he remember I think he wrote
about the fact that he asked Indira
Gandhi Madam Mrs Indira the then prime
minister of India that yo the Indian
people in Singapore are among the
highest performing people in the world
yeah they contribute so much to
Singapore and Indians elsewhere also
they they uh Stand Out Among all other
ethnic groups so why can't you do
something in India that will unleash the
potential of India yeah and the answer
from uh Mrs Gandhi was like no this is
the way it's going to be in India some
something to the to that uh effect uh I
don't know I don't remember the name of
the book but uh I have it somewhere yeah
so that's what he said so the thing is
that it's really easy to turn around a
small
Nation a city-state in a decade in two
decades very easy yeah but the larger
the system is the more inertia and
resistance it has from within especially
in the so-called federal system that we
have where we have so many different
centers of political power and one
Center of Central Power centralized
power which is not that powerful overall
it's very complicated the kind of system
we have created after 1947 right the
setup that we have created is designed
to prevent any rapid progress that's how
it is but it's it's certainly something
that can be worked upon and the more you
change it the faster the change will
happen but overall
the Chinese tried to emulate the
Singaporean system and now you can see
that it's kind of working to a certain
extent it takes a long time in a large
country yeah I mean if you have let's
say you have a helicopter no forget a
helicopter let's say you have a drone
that's the size of my hand you're gonna
turn it around make it flip it can flip
very fast but let's say you have the a
drone the size of a building you want to
make it flip it's going to take a long
time to slowly flip around yeah that's
how it goes any physical system
including any political system the
larger it is the slower it will move
around that's how it is so it's
certainly something that we can uh take
inspiration from the kind of reforms and
policies that a leak when you adopted I
do not agree with the fact that English
should be the unifying uh
unifying factor for India we are a 10
000 plus year old civilization our
unifying language our civilization
language has always been Sanskrit today
they they have created an enormous
amount of opposition to Sanskrit in
India and this is something that has
been created over the past 100 years
especially after 1947 especially after
the 1960s the political opposition to
Sanskrit from all quarters all kinds of
quarters yeah so it's gonna be an uphill
battle for India but eventually if India
is to regain its its civilizational
status as one of the as the preeminent
civilization it has to come back under
Sanskrit not English English is the
language of the oppressor of the
colonizer right now we use it that's
fine we use it against them that's all
right but eventually we have to return
to Sanskrit that is the one unifying
language we can have English is is it is
a stop Gap solution and it's not the
right solution
so yes India can certainly be unified
under one language but that that
language cannot be English it has to be
Sanskrit it has always been Sanskrit
yeah it is it is certainly possible we
have enormous an enormous amount of
cultural diversity and all that you go
to even within a certain State let's say
odisha you go from Northern orisha uttar
and you go to Southern the cuisine
changes the dialect the the way of
speaking changes the way of dressing
changes everything changes right so it's
it's it's so beautiful to have so much
diversity and yet we have always been
one civilization extending all the way
to Indonesia and the Philippines and all
that so the unifying Factor was Dharma
the dharmic culture and Sanskrit so
that's where India has to go back maybe
it will take 20 years maybe 50 years
maybe 100 years but that's the direction
in which India has to go if it has has
to ever like people keep on saying or or
uh what do they say transforming India
into Bharat or making India the vishwa
guru or making India the superpower or
it will not happen as long as we promote
English as the linked language English
is a foreign language it's the it's the
it's one of the worst remnants of
colonialism yeah and people like me are
most comfortable in English that's
that's the that's what's been done to us
yeah so English has to go but yes we can
certainly be unified wholly under one
language that can only happen under
Sanskrit even Hindi is not the right
language yeah the Hindi is not I mean
it's a very recent language it's a it's
a mongrel language a mixture you know
like they say in Hindi Hindi of various
things like like various turkic dialects
and some Arabic some Persian with
overall the structure in and syntax
the structure of the grammatical
structure of Sanskrit with the
vocabulary of all these foreign
languages that's what Hindi is Hindi is
something that emerged out of the turkic
Court the Mughal so-called Mughal God
and I eventually Hindi has to be phased
out Hindi is not the right language to
unify India I don't know who decided and
why they decided to use Hindi I think it
was the great magnificent Mr nehru who
did that so Hindi eventually has to go
it can only be Sanskrit as if India has
to rise again not English not Hindi it
has to be Sanskrit and I know I I I'm
sure I can I mean I can imagine what
kind of comments in in the chat will be
going on right now but that's fine this
is my view and that's the only way
forward
I'd like to know I'd like to ask about
the contribution so far of the whole
Bengali people from the period of time
period of the Epic itihasa such as
ramayan and Mahabharata until the
present day it saddens me now to read
about my own culture from so-called
history textbooks referred to us in the
school where they speak very less about
Bengal also I would like to ask uh how
effective it will be to install a new
mandatory law for the foreigners to
learn our national language first
starting from Sanskrit of course
whenever they intend to come to any
countries in the Indian subcontinent
because I'm asking because we have this
unfortunate status right now where
people must speak English for them to
understand and also available language
plays a big role in our identity and our
address as a nation
for example Punjabi Marathi Bengali
Tamil French German Etc they are known
from respective places for the mother
tongue they speak okay right my thoughts
so first of all let's speak about the
people of Bengal so Bengal is a
wonderful place it's got this incredibly
Rich wonderful history that that dates
back to the beginning of India itself
right Bengal is not some separate place
in the Bengal it's of separate people
it's never been that way right so we
know where Bengal is do I have to put it
in the map let's do it in case all right
we know where Bengal is you know
uh Bengal has been partitioned into
India and East Pakistan that was then
it's all went happened with the
partition in the early 20th century by
one of the English guys Kirsten was it
whoever it was and then today we have
Bangladesh and and uh West Bengal but
this entire region was once called Wanga
or anger so once we had the kingdom of
anger which was ruled by the crew
Dynasty the Anga mahajanapada and the
people of this mahajanapada the great
Republic we have to call the angayyas
right in the mahajanapada dates back to
the late Vedic era itself right The
Vedic eras many thousands of years old
so we had the great Anga mahajanapada
right then we had various kingdoms uh in
this region kingdoms like uh
Kingdom of the late Vedic period we had
uh the pundra kingdom of the Mahabharata
yeah which lasted all the way to the
mauryan times the infamous incident of
king of Emperor Ashok executing ordering
the execution of 18 000 Aji vikas
happened in pundra right
then obviously we we have the Wanga
Kingdom which is mentioned in the
Mahabharata in the ramayan in the
shastra of chanaki as well yeah so you
can see the oldest period is The Vedic
period Then you have the ramayan period
then then I would say the mahajanapada's
period Then the ma which would have
included the Mahabharata more or less
and then we have the more in Iran and
the modern era right so the Wanga
kingdom is mentioned in the ramayan in
the Mahabharata in the arthashastra the
anger kingdom is mentioned is one of was
one of the great mahajanapadas so you
can see how ancient the history is right
so um when you this region was from
various in during various time periods
part of the uh mauryan Empire part of
the Gupta Empire then you had the great
golden Kingdom right go to Kingdom from
roughly the third from the fourth
Century A.D to the middle of the 7th
Century A.D yeah the last thing was the
great king Shashank who died in the
middle of the seventh century or so and
then there was a period of about a
century of complete Anarchy and Chaos
that's what it was called and then you
had the Advent of the Pala Empire the
founder was gopala the first who was
democratically elected by the people to
put an end to the Machinery to the chaos
and Anarchy and the TV people themselves
elected this guy democratically as the
king of the of the Wanga region gopal
and he was the founder of the pal Empire
from the middle of the eighth Century
A.D and it lasted for about uh maybe 400
years roughly that sort of thing so
that's the kind of History this region
has had it's always been the history of
Bengal is intrinsically related to the
entire history of the entirety of India
it dates back to The Vedic times the
ramayan times the Mahabharata times the
mahajanapada Iraq the more in Era the
the
um the modern Empire the Gupta Empire
then you had all that so it's it's a
very rich beautiful history it was it it
historically was one of the most rich
the one of the most prosperous one of
the richest and fertile and abundant
regions of India beautiful culture
excellent education the great
vikramshila mahavihar or Universe great
victim university is in Bengal it's ruin
siren Bengal everything is ruined now
yeah it's not in present-day Bangladesh
if I'm not mistaken
beautiful history very rich history and
then you had the you had the destruction
of dalanda and the turkic conquest of
the region yeah and then things go south
and today we have Bangladesh and West
Bengal and let's let's uh end it there
so uh what's the other question yeah the
question is how effective would it be to
install a new mandatory law for
foreigners to learn about national
language starting with Sanskrit four
countries in the Indian subcontinent I
don't think Pakistan would ever agree to
making Sanskrit the mandatory language I
don't think Afghanistan would make it
what would would uh ever agree to that
I'm not sure even Bangladesh would agree
to that I'm not sure even West Bengal
would agree to Sanskrit that's the
problem that's the problem that's the
unfortunate status we that we have right
now we are so deeply divided within
within ourselves even within India we
are so divided but eventually this has
to happen we need to have a single
unifying civilization language which is
the and the only one that is that can
fit the bill is sanskrit
it's the oldest language it is also an
extremely adaptable language and a very
scientific and modern language yeah
so uh yeah that needs to happen
eventually but Bengal is a wonderful
place beautiful incredibly rich and
complex history and it's kind of sad to
see the direction it went in in the past
1000 years which is something that
happened to the entirety of India the
the Millennium of humiliation yeah so
yeah that's about that's about Bengal
yes
all right let's take some questions
about science for a change we hardly
talk about science these days yes so
let's see some questions about science
ishika says can we say that there there
is no matter without time and there is
no time without matter as we consider
the birth of the universe to be when
time started interesting question so yes
the universe
begins with what we call the Big Bang
Yes the the we initially had a
singularity or something close to a
singularity and then it expanded
outwards it expanded
the expansion of space-time
and that's that's the beginning of the
beginning of time so the moment of the
Big Bang or this or the Big Bang itself
is when time started from t equal to
zero and then it it goes on forward so
uh
so yes initially the universe was just
pure energy at the instant of the big
bang and then eventually the energy
coalesced into massive particles and all
that that's a whole long story yeah it
happened in the very initial moments
after the big bang so initially it's
pure energy most likely just photons and
gravitons and all that
um
so that's how it was so time has always
coexisted with mass energy
and you could also say that mass energy
is also coexistent with time but the
question is what happened before the big
bag and we don't quite have the answer
nobody has an answer uh there are people
like Roger Penrose who have spoken about
this uh the the concept of eons eons
yeah uh conforming cyclic cosmology
that's that's his theory Penrose
hammerhof uh so I'm not sure I'm not
really studied that so I'm not sure what
the concept of time is that when you go
back in time to before the Big Bang or
after the big grunge or whatever it is
so yeah typically time and mass energy
they go together yeah but we don't quite
know what time is is it something that
only that there is an artifact of our
Consciousness is it something we imagine
or is it something that emerges out of
the fabric of space time or is it
something that like like in quantum
mechanics time is an external parameter
in quantum mechanics time is a classical
parameter yeah so is time something
that's external to every universe as
well or is it something else entirely
does it emerge out of uh D coherence or
does it emerge out of entanglement
quantum entanglement no one knows yet
there are lots of theories that people
are struggling with but we want quite
know time what time is so yes as far as
we we are concerned from whatever we
understand time and mass energy have
always gone together why do I say mass
energy because mass and energy are
essentially equivalent equals mc squared
which is one of the most uh fundamental
equations in in modern physics like they
say yeah
1905 was it whichever area so yeah
that's the deal that's the deal
they just says are black holes therefore
eternity dude how do they follow the law
of conservation of energy black holes
are something that people really find
scary right these vacuum vacuum cleaners
which suck everything in which is not
quite the case black holes are just well
you could think of them as pure mass and
they take various forms you know there's
rotating non-retating black holes and
unrotating uncharged black holes like
the shorts still black holes then you
have the various other kinds of black
holes uh charged black holes rotating
black holes rotating and charge black
holes extremal black holes on all that
so
are black holes Eternal are they
infinite are they do they live forever
well not quite the case the smaller a
black hole is the hotter it is so it's a
thermodynamic object and the hot object
is going to radiate stuff so a black
hole actually radiates mass energy yeah
and if it radiates mass energy then it's
going to shrink in size this is what we
call Hawking radiation or black hole
evaporation so as a black hole
evaporates if if its temperature is
higher than the temperature of the
universe which is uh what is it the the
cosmic microwave background radiation
temperature then the black hole will
evaporate and shrink and the smaller it
gets the faster it evaporates eventually
it explodes and go and disappears into
nothingness so black holes are not
necessarily Eternal how do they follow
the conservation law of conservation of
energy because the black hole has a mass
yeah and that mass is conserved that
mass doesn't disappear anywhere yeah
when a black hole accrets something when
it swallows a star the mass of the star
is added to the star to the mass of the
black hole so the mass is conserved when
a black hole radiates energy Hawking
radiation you can calculate how much
energy is radiated and that is
subtracted from the mass when two black
holes merge there is this enormous
gravitational wave tsunami which takes
over some of the mass so the resulting
black hole is not quite the sum of the
masses of the two black holes but you
can but it overall it all adds up and
energy and mass are conserved mass and
energy are essentially equivalent yeah
so that's how it is so black holes are
not necessarily Eternal large black
holes supermassive black holes you could
say are Eternal because uh they are
colder than the
temperature of the universe the
temperature of deep space the cmbr
temperature and that's why they they get
larger over time the accrete radiation
and their lifetime essentially exceeds
the lifetime of the universe itself 13.8
billion years so large sufficiently
large black holes are essentially
Eternal more or less eventually as the
universe expands it will get it will get
colder and then those black holes will
become hotter than the
the temperature of the universe but
that's how it is so black holes are not
necessarily Eternal and they certainly
do follow the law of conservation of
mass and energy
Krishnan says the cultural symbol of
China is the dragon the dragon so what's
the cultural symbol of India is it the
Indian elephant lion tiger or peacock uh
yes the cultural symbol so to say of
China is indeed the dragon this uh this
imaginary Beast which is like a snake
that flies or or a great lizard which
with wings when Claws and Talons talents
like like an eagle
and I suppose it can spit fire as well
yeah so that's the the mythical creature
imaginary creature that is the symbol of
China
what's the cultural symbol of India well
the cultural symbol of India is
something that's Up For Debate
everything in India is Up For Debate
they even debate whether India is a
nation or a civilization or an idea yeah
so everything is up for the debate it
doesn't necessarily have to be an animal
yeah so when it comes to various other
nations well Russia's symbol is the bear
isn't it kind of it's The Unofficial
national symbol of Russia the bear for
for the US it's that that
fears and evil looking Eagle which is
kind of appropriate the bald eagle
um
for whales it's it's some kind of a
dragon again for England what's yeah the
three lions that they have on their
Crest or something like that so every
nation has some symbols for India uh the
West tries to portray India as an
elephant to show India as a slow moving
sleepy creature yeah uh
otherwise one could associate the
elephant the the tiger with India for
sure because it's something that's uh
India has the largest population of
tigers and historically ours has had
that yeah
so it could be the tiger the peacock
well yeah it's the national bird of
India if I'm not mistaken if I'm not
mistaken the peacock but yeah it's it's
a it's not quite appropriate to have the
peacock
you know this harmless little pretty
little bird not little but pretty bird
as a symbol of a Nation willing to have
something fiercer so it doesn't
necessarily have to be an animal
uh the swastik the symbol that's what's
the symbol the holy auspicious swastik
symbol could be the national symbol of
India it's something that's been
associated with India since the days of
of the Indus the Saraswati Sindhu period
of our history yeah so the swastik could
be that the om symbol could be that
yeah we could also have the Dharma
chakra which is something that's uh
that's common to all the dharmic paths
yeah the Dharma chakra we also have the
Ashoka the the lion standard of Ashoka
which is not bad Lions we like lions
yeah so it could be any of those things
I don't think there is any consensus we
keep on arguing and debating about
everything we should have something that
is not that that
portrays that evokes some majesty and
power not something that's sleepy and
slow like an elephant not something
that's pretty and harmless like a
peacock it could be possibly
uh possibly the tiger possibly the three
lion standard of uh of Ashok or
something that is uh
something like this swastika or or the
OB symbol or the Dharma chakra I think
eventually we need to find some some
consensus on this maybe the tiger the
Bangladesh is to try to claim that the
tiger is their national symbol well
that's all right but uh that's okay so
yeah I'm not sure what the symbol is we
have so many symbols we are the oldest
civilization we have been around for
more than ten thousand years yeah so a
civilization the civilization that's
that old is gonna have a whole lot of
symbolism you know symbols associated
with it so if you want to pick just one
symbol then maybe we should have a
nationwide poll in which case many weird
things will come into the picture also
that's how it is we we have too much
democracy we have too much debate we
keep on arguing about pointless things
we should settle on one great symbol
Majestic symbol maybe the tiger maybe
the Ashok lion standard and make that
the official symbol of India yes
okay let's go into geopolitics now
hardik says India has recently
fast-tracked worked work work for a 11
gigawatt hydropower Dam on the Xiang
river which is a tributary of the
brahmaputra of arunachal just 100 to 150
kilometers from a Chinese 60 gigawatt
Dam which is in Chinese occupied Tibet
north of the region
considering the overall cost of 1.13
lakh crore rupees for this damn project
how do you see this move by the
government do you believe that China and
India might go to war in the future for
fresh water resources of Tibet right
good question so let's look at the
region where is this region uh uh I'm
not sure where exactly this is but you
can see this enormous massive River the
brahmaputra over here
and you don't see much of it coming in
from from Tibet so more than 80 percent
of the Waters of the brahmaputra they
originate in the forests of arunachal
Pradesh yeah so if the Chinese cut off
the the yard long which is the Tibetan
word for Tibetan name for brahmaputra in
the divert it it's not gonna cause any
major problems for India or for
Bangladesh or or yeah it's not going to
cause any major problems
the thing is that they are damning up
the river Upstream
the river originates in the Tibetan
plateau and then it flows southwards
it's it enters arunachal Pradesh and
flows through Assam eventually into
Bangladesh where it merges with the
ganga because the Padma and it flows
into the uh sea of Kalinga or the Bay of
Bengal
so why is India constructing this large
Dam hydropower Dam on this this
tributary of the of the uh of the
brahmaputra just a hundred to 150
kilometers from the Chinese Dam
there are reasons for this and it's not
about uh the reason is very simple see
if the Chinese divert away all the water
we are fine with it because most of the
water of the river comes from arunachal
the Danger
is that the Chinese may do a certain
release of water which may cause a
shockingly large massive flash flooding
in lower lying uh in southern regions
like in India and arunachal or Assam or
elsewhere which could cause catastrophic
damage to India that is the real danger
and the Chinese have tried such dirty
tricks in the past in the early 2000s
maybe 2003 to 2004 they had dammed up a
river called the parichur river
somewhere in where was it arunachal was
it ladakh somewhere in in along the
Tibet border
and yeah there was a danger that this
artificial Dam would be broken and the
entire uh it would cause an enormous
amount of flooding and kill lots of
people
so when a nation
controls territory that's that's
upstream and at a higher altitude that's
always the danger that they can release
water suddenly without warning and cause
catastrophic damage to your territories
and and kill lots of people
so
if India builds a large enough Dam
uh
south of of the Chinese Dam then if the
Chinese release water without informing
us then we can catch it and we can
mitigate the the potential catastrophic
impact of this thing so I I believe that
the 11 gigawatt hydropower Dam we are
building is is gonna be a dam that can
take care of such an eventuality yeah if
there is a sudden release of water this
Dam will be able to absorb much of it
and the overall impact Downstream will
not be what otherwise it would be so
that I believe is one of the major
reasons why this dam is being
constructed close reasonably close to
the Chinese Dam in occupied Tibet yeah
then of course it's going to generate
hydroelectricity for us and all that so
so that's the deal the other question is
do you believe that China and India make
go to war in the future for fresh water
resources of Tibet I don't think so
because most of the water like I said in
the brahmaputra OR
itself so even if the Chinese completely
divert the river still more than 80
percent of the river water of the
brahmaputra will keep on flowing so
that's fine so I don't think it's
something that could lead to war there
are certain Indian so-called
geopolitical commentators including very
senior people who are scared mongering
right now you go to Twitter and see
certain accounts I'll not name them
because there's no need for that but
there are people including very senior
people who have written books who are
scared mongering who are trying to
create this this sense of panic in India
that the Chinese are are indulging in in
water Warfare against India and one of
some of these authors have written books
about about Chinese rivers and all that
so yep
so overall I don't think it's uh if the
Chinese diverted it's a problem the only
danger is if they play these dirty
tricks and release water all of a sudden
without warning so that's why we need to
have dams that can absorb the impact of
such unforeseen malicious sudden
releases of Water by China because the
Chinese
we know that they can't be trusted they
they can play any reconnaissance they
can blame the weather they can make any
any kind of excuse so that's the primary
reason I believe why this dam is being
constructed
foreign
Stevenson says Tibet never conquered
China LOL oh my goodness Tibet never
conquered China well James Stevenson has
decided that Tibet never conquered China
I I'm sure this is a comment from one of
my older videos where I must have said
that Tibet conquered China so what are
the facts so um so let's let's see what
the facts are right
there was a Tibetan King Tibetan Emperor
called three song dedson who lived in
the 8th and 9th centuries A.D who did
conquer China so Mr James Stevenson I
need to educate you about this let's say
put something on on the screen yes uh
let's begin with Wikipedia as always the
statutory warning to everybody my
friends is that don't trust Wikipedia
especially when it comes to Indian
history but I am putting this on the
screen just for reference because even
Wikipedia is telling the truth in this
case so let's put this on the screen yes
there is this article on Wikipedia about
the Tibetan Empire Tibetan Empire and uh
all that so there's a map here tibet's
influence on on the region uh let's go
to history and let's go to the reign of
three song De Chen
this three song that sent 756 80 to 797
A.D uh
so this guy was crowned Emperor with the
name three song that sin he took control
of the government when he attained his
majority blah blah blah uh in 755 China
had begun to be weakened because of the
anshi Rebellion started by an lushan in
751 A.D which would last until 763 A.D
almost more than a decade uh three song
that sounds rain was characterized by
the re-assertion of Tibetan influence in
Central Asia
regions of the west of Tibet paid homage
to the Tibetan Court
from that time onwards the Tibetans
pressed into the territory of the tongue
Empires reaching the Chinese Capital
changan which is modern day Xi'an in
late 763 A.D Tibetan troops under the
command of whoever occupied changan for
15 days and installed a puppet Emperor
while the other Emperor was in loyang
nanjao in Yunnan and all that remained
under Tibetan control from 750 to 794
and so on
and eventually they turned on the
Tibetan overloads and helped the Chinese
inflict defeat on the Tibetans so three
songs
conquered China and he took the capital
city changan Modern Day some people will
say that but they don't think he did not
take Beijing well Beijing was not the
capital at the time changan was the
capital okay so this is about son you
can look into it what was changan
changan is present Dayan is one of the
oldest cities in China uh the the first
emperor of China uh what was his name
let's see it's written here wait wait
wait wait it'll be written here here you
go kinshi Huang the first emperor of
China his Imperial Court was just north
of the modern day city of Xi'an yeah so
uh it essentially has been the one of
the oldest capitals of China it was
certainly the capital of China during
the time of the Tibetan Invasion yeah
and the famous Terracotta Army
of the Chinese emperor King shihuan
Huang is is in a mausoleum right outside
this city yeah so this was the old
historical capital of China changan this
is the capital to the Tibetans conquered
they installed a puppet Emperor over
here under the leadership of the Tibetan
Emperor three song ditzan so uh dear
James Stevenson unfortunately LOL but
yeah it's it's not quite the case the
Tibetans did indeed conquer China you
can certainly study more about it yeah
it's all out there in public domain I
don't understand why people just
when they come across some new
information they are not ready to fact
check it or verify it do a simple Google
search they will simply take the time to
write a comment and say hello it never
happened look it up it happened
all right next
says if India carries out a military
operation to take back p.o.k Pakistan
occupied Kashmir what will be the
reaction of the European Union
especially of America
the reaction will be that of a anger and
they will take action see Pakistan
is a vital territory that is controlled
by the West it has been created
artificially
for a certain geopolitical purposes
which are still being served let's take
a look at the map
uh yeah sorry let me put that on the the
the the
on the screen here's the map here we are
so this nation was artificially created
by the west by the British to cut India
off from Central Asia and because Jammu
and Kashmir had acceded to India they
had to ensure that some parts of Jammu
and Kashmir also went to Pakistan and
that's how we have been cut off
temporarily for now from Afghanistan and
Tajikistan and the rest of Central Asia
this was part of the great game right so
if India takes back poke India will
regain access to Central Asia which is
not good from the eyes of the West
because it's gonna create a whole domino
effect you know the see essentially
all these nations are Russia's strategic
backyard it's part of Russia's exclusive
zone of of influence Russia has a
routine military exercises with all
these nations so if India can access
Afghanistan and Tajikistan then the
Russians can build you know
infrastructure through the region and
they can start accessing the warm Waters
of the Indian Ocean which is something
the Russians have for centuries wished
to do right and obviously India will
have to take more than POC back because
the wakan corridor is a very mountainous
region willing to take essentially
Northern Pakistan back which uh needs to
happen anyway so that would be a
disaster from the West for the west from
their perspective so if India Today
carries out a military operation the
West will impose sanctions on India they
will portray us as warmongers in 1971
George W
George H.W bush the senior Bush who was
then the was the senior official at the
time he called India a war-mongering
nation in 1971. I have seen an old copy
of Time magazine or Newsweek or whatever
in which India was portrayed as a bar as
a war Monger in the words of George Bush
the senior George Bush
in 1971 when India was fighting a just
War it was where we had gone to war for
just causes it was a war initiated by
Pakistan and still they were calling us
War mongers so if India initiates
something imagine what they will call us
they will most likely impose sanctions
on India the way they've imposed Russia
they may even send aircraft carriers
strike groups and you know who knows
what they'll do so right now it is not
the right time for this to happen we
need to ensure that uh we need to do
this when the when the taking back of
Pok becomes inevitable you don't do
something when there is a high chance or
a high probability of of not succeeding
you do something when you are certain of
succeeding that's what you do it so we
have to engineer a situation a
geopolitical situation where we are so
powerful that it is inevitable that we
will take it it should fall into our lap
without us even even fighting for it
that's what we need to do the the mark
of a true leader is that he or she wins
without fighting and nobody even
realizes what happened that is the
greatest Victory when you win without
firing a single shot so India has to
maneuver itself into a position over the
next decade or whatever
where it is inevitable that this happens
we don't want to carry out a military
operation it should come back to us on
its own so we have to rise to that
status where the people of Pakistan
people of Pok start clamoring and
begging to be reintegrated with India of
course we don't want to reintegrate the
whole of Pakistan right now that may
take another 1500 years because of the
extreme radicalization there but poke in
Northern Pakistan is necessary we need
it back yeah for geostrategic purposes
for geostrategic reasons so uh right now
is not the right time for this in the
future things will change this is a DEC
a decade of very rapid change we're
going to see a very rapid geopolitical
changes in this decade and we need to
ensure that we rise economically and
militarily over this decade and I think
by the time this decade decade is out if
we play our cards right then this could
become more or less inevitable so that's
what needs to happen we don't need to
jump the gun and do something which is
Hasty and ill-advised and when it's not
the right time to do it we need to be a
little patient it's not going to take a
lot of time for us to retake p.o.k and
and Achieve our geopolitical objectives
you know and these are just causes these
are our territories they have been our
territories for 10 000 years so it's not
like we are stealing someone's territory
and doing something wrong
right
somnath Abhishek says in yesterday's
Indian interest podcast you mentioned
about having kids in the early 20s
what's your opinion on the cost of
living of sustaining a family in one's
early event is very good question most
people this age don't even earn a good
Primary School annual fees in a month
also population is one of the reason why
cost of living Corporation is increasing
in our country so yesterday I went into
detail about this I gave the example of
China I analyzed the example of China
and how their one child policy has
caused is has it has begun to cause a
demographic disaster and now the people
have kind of given up their protesting
passively against the Chinese government
by refusing to have children it's gonna
cause a terrible population crash in the
future the population's average age is
gonna be going to the 50s and 60s
eventually which is a disaster for any
country most people is going to are
going to be old which is it's a disaster
so we don't want to go in that direction
for that our birth rate their total
fertility rate should be at least 2.1 we
have dropped below that it's two now or
maybe less so we are slowly going in
that direction the window of demographic
opportunity for India is up to 2050. now
so that's why I said that we do
certainly need to reduce the population
but it should not happen in an
artificial and Hasty manner we should do
it over a century or two centuries this
is the long term game
our plans need to be measured in
centuries we have to be patient we are
ten thousand plus zero civilization a
century is nothing for us yeah many
things won't happen in our lifetime but
they will happen in the lifetime of our
descendants so that's what we have to
work work for we are links in a chain
and we do we have to show make sure that
we are strong links our part is done
properly so now the question is a very
good question I said yesterday that the
optimum thing to do is for young people
to have their children two children or
whatever they want to have at least two
I would say in their early twenties so
that by the time you're in your early
40s when you're at the peak of your
career your kids have grown up yes and
then you can truly focus on your career
and through through your whatever you do
in your career you can uh help the
country yeah and help India grow that's
what we need you reach the peak of your
abilities in career in life in the 40s
in the 20s and 30s you're still learning
as you go you're not really all grown up
that's how it goes you know so
so I said you should have your kids in
your early 20s and then get on with life
don't wait until you're in the 30s or
40s to have kids it's it's kind of late
it's gonna exhaust you kids it takes a
lot of energy and effort to raise kids
the question is a very good one that
most people who are young in their 20s
don't have much of an income they are
still struggling to find some some way
in life and if you have kids how are you
going to pay afford afford to pay for
them so I the the solution is this
but you need to rely on your parents on
your families see we have always had
this extended family system which is why
all the kids were always very well taken
care of now today unfortunately in this
post Colonial or still colonized India
there are only a few centers of
development in the country certain Tire
one metropolitan cities uh Delhi
Bangalore Mumbai Hyderabad Chennai and
all and there are some Tire two cities
there are three cities also coming up
but opportunities are few
so people are forced to migrate from
wherever they live to some large city
and then that's that's causing this
phenomenon of these nuclear families or
whatever
uh so what needs to happen is India
needs to develop so the entire two Tire
three cities also develop and you people
can stay with their parents and have the
same opportunities that other people
have in their own uh hometowns
and it's perfectly fine I would say to
stay with your parents in your 20s even
in your mid-30s yeah if you can do that
then at least your children are in a
safe space of course
assuming your parents allow this in the
U.S by the time you're 18 your parents
will throw you out that's why the
American society is so broken
U.S society is so broken because there
is no such thing as a family system once
you're 18 your parents will throw you
out on the streets doesn't matter what
happens to live in your car if you don't
have a if you can't afford to have an
apartment that's not how a civilized
society behaves and on Saturday sorry to
say this yeah
so
the problems are being caused by the
breakdown of the family system the
extended family system you don't need to
live in the same house as your parents
you can live nearby and whenever you're
working you can drop off your kids with
your parents grandparents love to be
around grandkids mostly most I would say
yeah
so
the the solution is that we have to rely
on our extended families
especially the elders that's what needs
to happen we need to ensure that our
family system which has evolved over
thousands of years stays intact we don't
want that to break up yeah
and yeah it's gonna be expensive you
know school fees are going to be
expensive maybe you can take the money
or borrow the money from your parents
and hopefully pay them back if possible
in the future that's what family is for
that's what parents and overall year of
your your extended family is for you
you're all here to help each other right
grow
so that's what needs to happen the
society has to be a strong cohesive
Society the family system has to be
robust we have to maintain it we have to
nourish it
what's happening is the opposite right
now especially with this wokeness that's
coming into Indian Society these days so
we need a blend of modernity and
tradition modernity in in terms of
technology and ease of life and and all
that but we cannot destroy the
foundation of our society in the name of
modernity
so it's it's definitely a challenge when
you have kids when you're when you're
very young when you're in your early 20s
you most likely won't be able to afford
everything you know the upkeep the
raising of the kids and school fees and
all well rely on your parents until you
are financially self self-sufficient
which can most likely happen by the by
your mid-20s or late 20s yeah and I'm
sure your parents won't
begrudge this they'll be happy to to
help out most parents are like this some
parents obviously may may have other
ideas but that's how it goes so I know
it's it's a challenge it's tough but we
have to do this
and in the long run you will realize
that if you have kids early it was it
was the best thing you could have done
yeah so yeah that's how it is
Anisha says can you explain the history
of Iraq in the Syria country the Iraq
conflict of the Syria conflict and
what's the solution to the problems of
that region okay let's take a look at
the map where is the map let's take a
look at Iraq in Syria we know where
India is subcontinent then westwards is
Iran
and then you have Iraq and Syria right
Iraq
touches the Persian Gulf obviously you
have Kuwait here and Syria is uh it it
has uh the coast the Mediterranean Coast
yeah so what's the history of this place
right
so let's let's not go back thousands of
years obviously you had Mesopotamia the
the most supported the Mesopotamian
civilization in Iraq Syria also has a
very old history but let's let's talk
about the history of the conflict here
so uh it all dates back to the end of
the first World War
World War one ended in the well
when did it end
late 1910s
it started in 1914 and ended around 1920
okay look up the dates look up the dates
so at the end of world war 18 1918 maybe
so at the end of World War One
uh the Ottoman Empire had been destroyed
the Western Powers destroyed the Ottoman
Empire which was anyway crumbling it was
crumbling since the 19th century so they
destroyed in and dismembered the Ottoman
Empire and they divided it up among
themselves they created there was this
thing called the League of Nations which
is the precursor to today's United
Nations okay so the League of Nations
which was entirely controlled by the
Western Powers it decided that there
should be something called a mandate
system so the Ottoman Empire will be
broken up into pieces and each of these
will be called a mandate and one piece
will be called the will be given to the
the British to rule the British Mandate
of Iraq it was called Iraq
and one part was given to the French
which became Syria so I think Iraq was
given in 1920 Syria was in 1918 or or
vice versa whatever it is that that's
not very important I'm talking about
cause and effect so Syria became a
French mandate and Iraq became a British
mandate why did the British want this
big piece of territory for themselves
they wanted this as a vasal state as a
buffer state for two purposes this
region is rich in oil and the British
wanted the oil just like the Americans
do today why did the Americans go to war
with Iraq for oil not for democracy and
freedom just see how many people are
killed through carpet bombing so it's
all about the oil
so the British wanted control over Iraq
to present the Iraq firstly for the oil
and secondly because they wanted to
safeguard the Suez Canal which was the
umbilical Court of the British Empire at
the time yeah at the time they still
controlled India and they needed safe
Passage through through the sways region
also ways the sewage Canal so the
proximity to to this region gave them uh
it was it was good for them so that's
why they wanted Iraq so they took over
the Mandate of Iraq uh the Mandate of
Iraq in
1920 or so and the French took over
Syria in 1918 or somewhere around there
let's say 1920 roughly yeah
uh then eventually I think by 1928 or
1938 or so the the British so supposedly
gave freedom to Iraq but they kept on
interfering in the internal affairs and
they kept on controlling the oil
production and all that until when
um
1950s or something yeah I think until
1958 the sways crisis happened in 1956
in the British were in control of the
oil production and various other things
in Iraq until 1958 and after that I
think the Americans kind of started
putting their fingers in in the pie and
the Americans started controlling Iraq
you had all these revolutions and
um schools and all that in Iraq
eventually the bath party uh took over
Saddam Hussein took over was allied with
the U.S he was a massage of the
Americans and the Americans were very
happy with him yeah for for a
significant amount of time in Syria what
happened is that uh
uh there were these various uh there was
various governments came and went I
think in 1970 there was a bloodless coup
and uh Basha no sorry
Assad came to power he was a military
guy there was a bloodless who he came to
power he Allied Syria with with the USSR
he Allied Syria with the USSR and Syria
became active in the regional
geopolitics uh so hafez al-assad died in
2000 uh even though Syria had aligned
with the USSR they
allied with the U.S in the first Gulf
War
to to liberate Kuwait from Saddam
Hussein that's interesting
so senior Assad died in 2000 and his son
the junior Russia Assad hafez
Bashar Bashar al-assad came to power
yeah it's a dynastic succession
um
and then in 2011 there was this
so-called Arab Spring which were these
color revolutions instigated by the
Americans across the Arabian countries
there was one in Egypt and other places
as well Libya was destroyed by the
Americans Gaddafi was was assassinated
and and various other color revolutions
throughout the Arab world so the
Americans tried a similar thing in Syria
as well there was this so-called
outpouring of of uh protests and unrest
against the the authoritarian rule
supposedly of of Assad that was the
Syrian civilian War so Assad the father
and the son they are both a part of a
minority community in Syria so Syria has
this mixture see these are artificial
Nations as you can see you have straight
borders you know straight lines wherever
you have straight lines you have
artificial borders and wherever
artificial borders have been created
Every Nation becomes a mix of
ethnicities which is unnatural and which
is something that generates unrest in
Civil Wars and that's why all these
regions are so so messed up so in Syria
you have Sunni Muslims you have
Christians you have goods and you have
the alawi people the alawites the
alawites are have traditionally been
oppressed by by the sunnis the alawites
are shias they're also influenced
historically by Christianity and
Zoroastrianism
and the alavis are about 10 to 12 of the
population of the of Syria the assads
are allowis
they are alawites so there are minority
who rule Syria and they that's been used
to to create unrest in Syria among the
Sunni Muslims and other people so in
2011 the Americans instigated a civil
war in Syria and uh and so significant
portions of the country fell to the
so-called Rebels including Al-Qaeda who
were fighting on behalf of the U.S and
many other coalitions and forces
um in 2015 the Russians under Vladimir
Putin intervened in Syria yeah at this
time you had U.S troops in Syria the
Russians then intervened in Syria
they've got Russian troops and Russian
material and aircraft
Etc that uh came into Syria there is
this port
in Syria Latakia where you have uh where
at times the Russian aircraft carrier
has been parked and Russian warships
have been there
so after 2015 the tide turned because of
Russia thanks to Russia and the
Americans eventually withdrew their
forces from from Syria
but then they asked turkey to get
involved so the Turks have got involved
in Syria they have occupied I think the
north eastern part of Syria which is
currently under Turkish occupation
and that's the kind of situation you
have in Syria right now overall basad
al-ashar is mostly secure thanks to the
support of Russia and Vladimir Putin
and right now the Americans are fighting
a proxy war in Northern Syria through
turkey through the Kurds because the
Kurds have always wanted a free uh their
own Homeland in this region so that's
the deal that's the kind of History
Syria has had that's the history of the
Syrian conflict it's not yet over
because it's you know to end the
conflict you have to cut off funding
and cut off support to what's happening
but that's not the case so Syria is kind
of still in in a state of Civil War to a
certain extent but uh asab is now more
or less in control of most parts of the
country and now it's kind of a civil war
kind of in a very small way like what's
happening in Ukraine through through
proxy yeah so the Turks are the American
proxy in Syria and the Turks have these
expansionist Tendencies so they're happy
to occupy parts of other countries right
so uh like the drugs have occupied parts
of Cyprus and they're also playing games
against Armenia they keep threatening
Greece so turkey is happy to do to to
play this role
in the case of Iraq we know what
happened to Saddam Hussein and now Iraq
has been totally destroyed and I don't
even know who's in power there it
doesn't really matter they're all
puppets
so that in in brief is is the history of
Iraq in the Syria conflict what's the
solution the solution is for the
occupying forces the Western powers to
get out of the region
and then it will take some time a few
decades maybe a century or two for the
region to realign itself naturally these
processes take time once the external
influence goes away the colonial
Imperial influence goes away
then things can realign themselves
readjust themselves on their own but
that takes time it's it's often messy so
all these problems that have been
created across the world by the by the
westerners all these nations that have
straight-line borders which are
completely artificial and unnatural
these are gonna create conflicts in the
future after the Western influence has
been taken away it's gonna take a long
time for things to go back to the
Natural order this is a recipe for civil
war and disaster and worse across Africa
across the Middle East and even in the
Indian subcontinent that's what they've
done they have planted the seeds for
maybe a couple of centuries of conflicts
and it's it's their intervention is
still happening the Western
Interventional in all these regions so
it's it's gonna be a long time before
things go back to to the way they showed
the natural order of things the solution
is for the West to disengage and
withdraw and let these nations and the
peoples
in the cultures you know figure it out
among themselves through whatever means
is necessary
to to
you know the the future that they want
and it's that's gonna first go through a
phase of conflict multi multiple
conflicts possibly
that's how it is that's that's the dirty
game they've played
Subway says what are your views on
Indians considering the us as the
biggest threat threat after China and
how has the Russia Ukraine war changed
the perspective of Indians because many
Indians learned geopolitics after the
invasion and got to know how geopolitics
works I think Indians are still figuring
out figuring out how geopolitics works
but Indians are no longer that naive
nowadays which is visible from the fact
that they now Indian most of the
respondents considered the us as the
second largest military threat to India
after China if you had asked Indians in
19 in in 2017 they would have said
Pakistan is the number one threat
most Indians until 19th until 2017
viewed Pakistan as the number one threat
to India then you had the doklam doklam
crisis then you had the galwan Clash
then China came into Focus then all the
news media started focusing on China and
then China came into the national
Consciousness and now Indians understand
that China is the primary threat
Pakistan is just a proxy of other other
forces so Pakistan exists as long as it
serves certain purposes and it is
propped up right now but the West
previous state was China
now Indians I think are beginning to
realize this especially people watch
this channel understand this
um and the Russia Ukraine war has
certainly changed the perspective of
Indians to some extent if you watch the
Indian news media even today you watch
any Hindi news channel or most English
news channels they report as if it's
it's their reporting on behalf of the
West it's it's p they're purely aping
and copying the Western topic talking
points
most of the reporting in India is still
extremely silly like they have no
opinion of their own they just watch
what's being said on on British news or
the or the American news and then they
say the same things in Hindi or in in
some other way in English that's
typically what's what it means there are
a couple of major Indian English
language news channels that send their
reporters to the Ukraine conflict region
and they reported everything from the
Ukrainian side of the conflict if you
want to have balance reporting send a
couple of people also on the Russian
side of the conflict and report from
both sides then we know what's happening
no they won't do it that way and they
call it great reporting so the Indian
media is is like um I I don't have any
anything much nice to say about them
yeah but yes Indians are now slowly
realizing
about geopolitics
possibly because of the role that Dr Jai
Shankar is playing in the entire thing
he's probably one of the most active and
most impactful diplomats in the world
right now he is putting forth India's uh
perspective uh firmly without without
devolving into what we call the wolf
Fourier diplomacy that the Chinese
involving indulgent which is rather a
nasty and and it's unpleasant Dr
jashankar is is none of that he's a very
uh
very firm Diplomat but he is very
eloquent and he's very persuasive
obviously the West is not going to be
persuaded but at least it's educating
Indians as to what India's national
interest is and where India's interests
Lie from the geopolitical perspective on
the big global scale so I think Dr Jay
Shankar has played a major role in
educating Indians yeah uh I think he has
acquired a significant fan following and
that's I mean he should have more fans
actually considering the incredible role
that he's playing so yeah I think uh it
is much of it is thanks to Dr Jai
Shankar and because of the see what we
call the judgmental Doctrine eventually
after all is the Modi Doctrine doctor is
cutting out
the policies that Mr Modi wants him to
carry out from 2014 to 2019 it was Mr
Modi who was a de facto foreign minister
of India Mr Modi was The Defector
foreign minister of India most of it was
being done by him despite us having an
actual uh nominal foreign minister no
disrespect to anyone involved I'm just
saying that if you look at facts Mr Modi
was doing the bulk of the work of the
foreign Ministry and Mr Modi was doing
it extremely effective effectively but
now he has been able to uh delegate this
work to an extremely capable person and
that's great for us so that tells you
the value of having a professional
as a foreign minister as opposed to a
politician who takes up the job because
they they want power of status or
whatever I'm not I'm not pointing
fingers at anybody by the way okay
so uh so things have changed a lot after
the UK conflict happened be in India we
have started looking elsewhere we always
looked at Pakistan then in the last two
three years of China but now we are
looking elsewhere as well and we are
beginning to understand Indians the
Indian young people especially are
beginning to understand how the game is
played it's all about power it's all
about resources it's all about control
when now we are beginning to understand
what role the economy plays what role
the military plays all that it's it's
great to see this we are most Indians
are still learning but at least we are
seeing them waking up now and the
results of this poll that you're
mentioning is kind of an indicator that
Indians have kind of woken up now and
Indians are not that naive anymore a
year ago I used to get really frustrated
how naive Indians are yeah
that's not the it's not quite the case
today people have really woken up so I'm
really really happy to see that
says uh Iran doesn't have very good
relations with turkey and Pakistan why
doesn't Iran support the Kurdish
independence movement or the Balochistan
Independence Movement all right let's
take a look at the map everything
becomes clear when you look at the map
this is if you learn nothing from this
channel you'll please learn this you
want to understand a nation's foreign
policy look at the map the map will tell
you what the foreign policy should be so
let's take a look at the map
right we are talking about Iran and
we're talking about the Kurdish movement
and the Balochistan Independence
Movement yes
so uh where is Balochistan where is
Kurdistan I think that's what we have to
ask ourselves Let's uh close that for a
second
and let's
let's see Balochistan
let's do a Google search for that
foreign
and let's put that on the screen so that
uh you get a you get the context
all right let's put this on the screen
Kurdistan let's go to the map
of what Kurdistan is this is what
Kurdistan
ought to be the light colored region
that you see in the screen let me Begin
by this
okay this is a bigger
okay there we go
so the Kurdish inhabited Kurdish
majority region
is the light colored region as you can
see it encompasses parts of Iran large
regions of Anatolia present in Turkey
temporarily maybe not parts of Syria and
parts of Iraq so the Kurdish people
don't have a nation of their own they
are divided into four or five countries
that their their territory is divided it
has been taken over by four or five
countries turkey Iran Iraq and Syria and
some of it is even in in Azerbaijan
Armenia maybe yeah
so that's the deal so why would Iran
support Kurdish Independence if it would
mean that the Iranians would have to
give some territory for this independent
nation why would they do that the Kurds
the Kurdish people are not an Arabic
people they are an indo-iranian people
or the west Western historians would
call them an Iraq iranic people and
Iranian people they used to be
historically zoroastrians or something
else perhaps maybe something even before
Zoroastrianism but today they are
Muslims but they are not Arabs so they
are very they have very close cultural
and ethnic ties with the people of Iran
the Persian people and yet Iran occupies
about maybe a quarter of their territory
so if Iran were to support support
Kurdish Independence it would mean that
Iran would be willing to give up this
Kurdish portion of its territory and
that is something no Nation will ever
ever do so that's why Iran doesn't
support Kurdish Independence now let's
talk about Balochistan
let's talk about Balochistan once again
we go to images and let's see the map of
Balochistan let us Begin by this
this is the biggie fight map imbecund
this is the Immigrant map so
this is the ethnic the a map of ethnic
groups in Western India and now
temporarily whatever Nations there are
yeah so the dark brown thing is Punjab
which was historically the territory of
Maharaja Ranjit Singh which the British
have given up given to Pakistan
illegally yeah this brown territory has
always been was the Sikh Empire
I don't understand why it was given to
to Punjab actually I do understand why
but it was not right synth is yellow
green is the Pashto dominated region and
the pink is Balochistan do you see where
Balochistan is it is
it is in Pakistan parts of Afghanistan
and a significant portion of it is
occupied by Iran
you could say that at least a third of
Balochistan about a third of Balochistan
is currently occupied by Iran
yeah you go to chabahar you go to this
region you will see Balochi people there
who have right now Iranian citizenship
so if Iran were to support the
independence apology they would have to
give up this pink portion of their
territory as well so why would they do
it
and this is one of the reasons why India
is right now not playing to is not
playing this Balochistan Independence
card too strongly because if India were
to support Independence it means that we
would also support the secession of the
Iran Iranian portion of Balochistan yeah
I mean uh
morally we were they would have to do
that or whatever so that's why that's
one of the reasons why India is not
going down that road right now because
we we have good relations with Iran and
we we need we have a certain convergence
of geopolitical interests with Iran so
let's not go down down the road so Iran
doesn't have good relations with turkey
or Pakistan but they will not support
the independence for the Kurds and they
will not support Independence for
balochism because they hold they they
have taken over territories of both
these peoples and why should they give
it up no Nation ever does that so that
is the reason
why Iran will not support the Kurdish
independence movement or the Balochistan
Independence Movement there is good
reason for them not to do that
interesting
of course it's interesting next question
Daniel Nicholson says when India and
China eventually and inevitably rise as
the
civilizations how would Europe compete
to remain affluent as they are today
firstly
it's gonna be either India or China
eventually it's not going to be both
it's not going to be both there's
there's only room for one top dog
in the world at any given point
sometimes you have this this bipolar
situation but it's typical in Nations
that are situated geographically far
apart two Nations that are like today
India and China are essentially
neighbors temporarily because the
Chinese have have occupied Tibet yeah so
that's that is going to come to a head
eventually eventually it's going to be
either India or China okay
now the question is what what will
happen to Europe how will Europe compete
ask yourselves this one question forget
about Russia Russia is not part of
Europe Russia isn't is an Eastern
culture okay
let's talk about Western Europe uh
what's what's part of NATO
uh nato in the EU that is the Europe we
are talking about ask yourselves this
very simple question what do these
nations produce
what natural resources do these nations
have do they have large quantities of
oil do they have large quantities of gas
do they have large quantities of iron or
copper or any minerals or coal or or any
such thing do they produce large
quantities of food grains
these nations overall if you put them
together they have next to nothing in
terms of Natural Resources or any such
thing the reason why they are so
incredibly affluent is because of the
past five centuries of colonization and
loot and plunder of mainly India and
also Africa and other nations and of
course of course the Americas yeah
so the reason why these nations are so
affluent is because of theft and plunder
and genocide and colonization and of
course they use the money to build
themselves themselves up and create all
these systems and obviously they've done
a good job of using the money to to
create this extremely Advanced Society
these extremely Advanced societies yeah
so one has to give it to them that once
they stole the money they were they were
able to put it to good use but
eventually when either India or China
rise and they become the preeminent
civilization
and they establish a different kind of
world order as opposed to the to the to
the U.S rules-based World Order which is
a neocolonial world order new Imperial
World Order once India or China imposes
their world order on the world which
will happen within 50 years or 100 years
most likely
then these guys will have no other
source of income even today Africa is
being plundered
as if it was still colonized you don't
realize this yeah because it's it's done
in a very nice way by proxy
I mean Eastern of Western Africa Mali
Etc has some of the world's largest gold
reserves but these countries are dirt
poor While most of their gold is in
France how does that happen it's called
neocolonization so once this system of
theft and plunder and Neo Imperialism
and neo-colonization is ended
Europe will inevitably decline
and go back to where they have always
belonged you know
Europe has historically never been the
most prosperous region
they went through the rise of Europe
only happened in the past 500 or so
years before that Europe was never
prosperous look at the GTP charts of the
past 2000 years Angus Madison look at
them yeah I'm not going to put in the
screen you can do that much homework
yourself look up the GDP charts and see
in the past 2000 years which European
nation had anything like the GDP of one
tenth of India or one tenth of China
none of the European nations had it if
you put the whole of Africa together it
did not add up to India's GDP and so on
So eventually as either India or China
Rises to the top Europe is gonna Decline
and it since it doesn't really produce
anything intrinsically it's gonna go
into poverty eventually and especially
when they will have no other place to
plunder that's how it's going to go and
yeah the world is going to change a lot
and we are with beginning witnessing the
beginnings of that we are witnessing the
beginnings of that we are in a way
living through a very dangerous and
difficult time very turbulent time but
on the other hand we are also very
privileged to witness these changes
happening in real time typically such
changes happen over decades or centuries
we are witnessing this happen week upon
week month upon month year upon Year by
the time the 2020s end the world is
going to be a very different place take
it from me
right
okay two questions about a similar topic
grave Walker says your opinion on the
recent find of Indian DNA in Greece from
1500 BCE and the decipherment of linear
a script using Linear B script reveals
Sanskrit oh my God what is this did
Mithani groups go further from Syria or
is it something else descended from
Rigby Clans asks very good questions a
paper was dropped on 17 January with 106
samples on Ancient Greek ancestry and 66
samples are from the island of Crete
um where bharathia language are offering
saffron to a goddess as depicted in the
ancient minoan period 1600 BCE these
samples have 13 to 10 percent bharatiya
ancestry we have the examples of zebu
cattle uh Griffins Indus Valley
Griffin's Shield lapis largely ring
found on the Nino one sites
culture have similarities in Hydro
Technologies according to a 2020 paper
what's my thoughts about these evidences
all right good question so I have
recently come up across the paper I
haven't studied in detail but let's
first take a look at what this region is
where where is this region the island of
Crete in the minoan region
where is it so we know where India is
yes all right let's Orient ourselves
let's go slowly Westward so that we can
keep up go west we have Iran go west we
have Iraq Syria then we enter the
Mediterranean Sea region we have
Anatolia which is currently called
turkey mostly and then you have the
island of Crete kriti
it's historically being a Greek island
you have the great minoan civilization
in this region yeah the minuan
civilization dates back to about 3500
BCE that's the beginnings of the minoan
civilization so the Milan civilization
was around these islands in the agency
Crete and the Aegean Sea Islands it was
a seafaring uh island-based civilization
it was a you could say you could say
it's a it was a kind of Greek sort of
civilization or a pre-greek civilization
right
so uh which now so now that we have
oriented ourselves let's take a look at
the paper that we are referring to where
is the paper
ancient DNA reveals something add
mixture of things
here it is here we go
let's a
hide this for a second ancient DNA
reveals admixture history and endogame
in the prehistoric agency region
and uh it's a 102 ancient individuals
from Crete the Greek mainland and the
Asian Islands spanning from the
Neolithic to the Iron Age and all that
and there's a detailed description of
the findings
and you can find this is the region that
they're talking about the points are the
places where from where they found the
uh samples and all that so we will not
go into the details of the paper but it
becomes clear that about 10 to 13 or
whatever of these samples have Indian
ancestry they call it and the money's
DNA or whatever but it's Indian ancestry
you know they they use terms that are
extremely misleading and confusing for
most people so the thing is that this
this is Indian and let's talk about the
monkeys right the langurs uh let us talk
about the language found on Santorini
Island
uh once again
let's put that on the screen here we are
Santorini Santo
Rini
langurs
so there are these paintings ancient
paintings on Santorini Island that
depict very strange monkeys that are not
found in the region the monkeys monkeys
are depicted as bluish in in nature
their faces have a different color
darker faces and they have this
incredibly curved tails yeah
then eventually the scientists realized
the researchers realized that these are
Indian langurs Hanuman langurs
yeah here is another Fresco uh there are
more murals of these monkeys yeah and
these monkeys are found in India not in
the Mediterranean region not in the
Asian region
so uh that's the that's the surprising
founding that what that people uh
realized recently so this is an article
from 2020 it's from uh physics portal
solving the Greek monkey mystery gave us
an important clue to the Bronze Age
world uh they talk about the aqua Theory
excavations the blue monkeys and all
that and they eventually realized that
these were Indian Hanuman monkeys they
thought it was baboons or verbets or
Griffith monkeys African species and all
that
uh but then they found the Tails and all
that and where is it Hanuman language
eventually they realize these are
Hanuman langurs right so how did Indian
monkeys end up all the way in Santorini
and the agency is the question so first
of all that indicates that uh
this 3600 year old city
had ties with ancient India at that time
we had the Saraswati Sindhu or so-called
Indus Valley Civilization period of
Indian history
right uh so that's a deal and now we
have this paper that talks about uh the
fact that uh certain percentage of these
P these samples uh 13 or so have Indian
ancestry Indian ancestry so not only
Indian monkeys but Indian genetics are
found in this region and this dates to
to about 1700 BC to about 1000 BC yeah
these samples the date range of the
samples is from about 1700 to about 1000
BC in the agency region of present-day
Greece now we know that in this region
we had the minnow one civilization the
minoan civilization dates back to about
3500 BC it lasted till about 1000 BC so
this is definitely smack bang in this uh
times time period
so either the Minoans themselves had
Indian ancestry or you or you could look
at uh neighboring kingdoms and Empires
we had the mithanis and the Hittites
so so the the agency region is here and
close to it we had the the mitani that
we have spoken about multiple times who
clearly were of Indian origin the
Mithani uh Kingdom in in Syria and
Anatolia yeah this region here
if you can see my mouse pointer we also
have the Hittites who are most likely of
Indian origin uh they lived in Anatolia
west of the mithanis yes and the
mithanis date back to what about 1800 BC
starting point and the Hittites date
back to about 1700 BC starting point
Syria and Anatolia uh most likely the
mitani and the Hittites had Indian uh it
is almost certain that they had Indian
ancestry the mithanis uh were an
indo-aryan so to say
aristocracy that ruled over the local
horian population
so that's quite close to the agency
region
and it's possible that uh the Indian
ancestry came in from either the
mithanis or the Hittites it's also
possible that it came it originated with
the Minoans themselves dating back to
four thousand to to almost 3500 BC now
then there is this other thing this new
paper that's been published or that is
what
is being referred to by gravewalker yeah
decipherment of linear a using Linear B
script so in in the agency region in the
minoan culture there have been they have
found two scripts one is linear a and
one is Linear B Linear B clearly is an
ancient form of Greek okay but linear a
has never been kind of deciphered until
you come to this paper this article from
and
now it appears that you have Sanskrit
words that are being attested that are
being attested in this script
so it looks like linear a was used to
write either Sanskrit or a closely
related descendant language in
indo-aryan language so they have found a
Indo evidence of indoor iron dialect in
10 minoan linear a inscriptions so let's
take a look at the inscriptions uh they
they have all these so there are words
like uh talasa this is the Greek
uh script but it says talasa Lobby
and so on so uh these Greek words
apparently have a Sanskrit etymology or
origin
uh and yeah so this paper talks about
that
so this paper has
so you can read the paper and it looks
like linear a was used to write either
Sanskrit or an indo-aryan language so
once again
this points to an out of India migration
in deep Antiquity we know what happened
4 200 years ago which is uh the 4.2 kilo
year event this the century of drought
across most of the world which kind of
ended the the which uh dried up the
Saraswati River and made people
dispersed from the Saraswati Sindhu
region in westwards as well as eastwards
yeah and which coincides with the
appearance of Indian zebu cattle in in
the so-called Fertile Crescent region
which again is adjoining this agency
region so these are all coincidences
that add up together
so most likely it is either the mithanis
or the Hittites or maybe the Minoans
themselves who had Indian ancestry and
now it with when you take the evidence
of the decipherment of the linear a
script which seems to be either Sanskrit
or a very closely related language then
it is possible that the Minoans
themselves were of Indian ancestry at
least the ancestors and then they may
have intermixed with the local
populations as well but the overall
culture remained the original culture
which eventually morphed into what is
now Greek culture or or pre-greek
culture or whatever yeah so yeah that's
that's the kind of evidence we are
finding as these pieces of evidence add
up it points more and more in One
Direction that there were multiple out
of India migrations
as opposed to an into India Aryan
Invasion migration picnic tourism
whatever it was out of India
out of India uh flow of genetics and
culture and languages yeah so yeah it's
it's a very interesting uh new
development and I still have to read the
entire paper in detail but very
interesting
so that's that's the preliminary
uh Impressions and thoughts that I can
offer to you
they just says why did the Arabs and
Turks and mughals not dissolve into
Indian culture like the kushans and the
shakas and the Greeks did
good good good question we just spoke
about the fact that the Greeks may have
Indian ancestry right and if you look at
ancient Greek culture it was a
polytheistic culture the Greek pantheon
of gods is a copy of The Vedic Pantheon
of gods the greatest god Jupiter oh
sorry Zeus pattern is nothing but Josh
pitrow of the which is the old Rigby the
God but Zeus Peter also has elements of
Indra the Thunderbolt the vajra right
the hammer the hammer is kind of latent
in this but yeah
so Greek culture if you go back to the
origins it kind of originates in Indian
culture so when the Greeks are
after the failed disaster of Alexander's
invasion of India attempted invasion of
India then you had the seleucid mauryan
war which was kind of a handshake kind
of thing how I get nice to know you and
then
the mauryan emperor empire and the
seleucid Empire became allies very
strong allies with family relations yeah
intermarriage and all that and then
after the dissolved dissolution of the
seleucid empire in the north west of
India let's put the map on the screen
because that that's what helps us
understand things where's the map
back to the map
so then you had these indo-greek
Kingdoms in gandar in Northwestern India
present-day Afghanistan
in the western Pakistan Northern
Pakistan all that right present day
and these Greeks these these rulers of
these regions were originally of Greek
ancestry and then they intermingled with
the local people the local Indians and
they became very much Indian yeah and
they anyway were polytheists in their
culture even true if you go back in time
originated in India itself most likely
so it was not hard for them to
harmoniously integrate themselves into
Indian society and people if they ask
where are the Greeks today well they are
all Among Us
most people in these regions northern
and western India would have fractional
Greek ancestry maybe half a percent
maybe one percent yeah and it's it won't
be visible at all and the Greeks are
anyway not very different
not very European as such yeah
so that's about the Greeks the kushans
they originated in uttarakuru
the kingdoms of uttarakuru were
indianized kingdoms they were of Indian
origin themselves we know that
which is present-day Central Asia these
were all indianized regions and the
original inhabitants were of all were
all of Indian origin of course they
these were Nomads especially the shakas
the skitians they were Nomads and they
they roamed as far as Eastern Europe
they conquered parts of Eastern Europe
and much of these regions the entire
Central Asian step and they intermingled
and um and and mixed up with people of
Europe as well so that's what happened
but overall the kitchens were sun
worshipers and when they re-entered
India they also were able to integrate
very harmoniously with Indian Society
without any friction that is known of at
all I mean there is no historical record
of any uh ethnic friction or Strife or
any such thing they just assimilated
harmoniously into Indian society and
they were great rulers uh for for the
time that they ruled India the uh
Northern chatrap was in the western
right the Western were the Great uh
Lords and Protectors of the greater
yotherling of somnath and so on
so the skitians were also of Indian
origin and they were also politics and
same goes for the kushans yeah when it
comes to the Arabs and Turks the mughals
are Turks themselves they came from a
very different see initially there were
these these homes who invaded India
which are The Originators of the what of
the later Turks the homes eventually
some of them became Turks they later
became known as Turks so we have the
turkishahi dynasties in India
in in mainly gandar Afghanistan that
actually defended India for a couple of
centuries against the turkic invasions
the initial turkey conventions yeah
so even the hoons were able to
assimilate very harmoniously into Indian
Society despite being a very different
ethnicity yeah the mongolic ethnicity
essentially
uh the Turks and the Arabs the Turks
were essentially the descendants of
homes but they were islamized
so they were monotheists they were they
they practiced abrahamic uh culture so
did the Arabs and that is very different
from any polytheistic culture and that
is something that can not integrate
itself easily into a polytheistic
culture so that's what happened it's
because of this very Stark difference in
the culture of the Arabs and the Turks
that they were not able to integrate
themselves into Indian Society the way
all other
visitors were able to yeah
so that's the answer sir in short
Shaheen says do you agree that the
Japanese goddess benzathin in the
Persian Persian God is anahita are just
other different versions of Saraswati
because they are very similar to
Saraswati anahita was called
okay let's let's uh put some of that on
the screen yeah I have some stuff here
let's put that on the screen so let's
talk about anahita first
the origins of the person goddess
anahita
the original name was
essentially a way of saying Saraswati
anahita is a river goddess yeah
um
so oh yeah it says here
what's the name of an indo-iranian
cosmological figure uh goddess of the
waters fertility wisdom healing in this
depiction she is on a lion I think and
she has a son behind her or a hello
this is a portion or Greek kind of
depiction of anahita Aphrodite in the
guise of Aphrodite the Greeks borrowed
this uh conflation with Ishtar which is
a Semitic Divinity and all that but this
is nothing but the Persian version of
Saraswati because the Divinity is
unattested in any old western Iranian
language establishing characteristics
prior to the introduction of the
russianism in Western Iran is very much
in the realm of speculation
Devotion to the goddess even evidently
survived their conversion to
zoroastanism which means that this is a
pre-zoroastrian goddess the accommenid
dynasty converted to
zurasem from which religion from
Hinduism obviously the original portions
were Hindus himself was born a Hindu
right so it's it's clear that this is a
Saraswati the Persian version the
Persian form of Sarasota now let's talk
about benzite and shall we
so this is from Encyclopedia Britannica
benzitin or Ben 10 they call it uh so
this is one of the seven gods of luck or
divinities of luck in Japanese culture
um the Buddhist Patron goddess of
literature and music and wealth and
femininity which is nothing but
Saraswati uh all that uh
she is identified with the Indian
goddess Saraswati also a patron of
literature in the Arts who probably
traveled to Japan along with Buddhism so
Buddhism brought with it Hindu gods and
goddesses into Japan and uh there are
seven gods major gods in Japan
so bishaman let's take a look at
bishaman bishamon or Bishop monten is
essentially kuber the Buddhist version
of kuber or vesh shravana all right
let's see who who will we have uh
daikoku daikoku
is mahakala the Hindu god Shiva in his
aspect as time the great destroyer and
so on and so forth so it's clear that
bin zaithin is let's take a look at what
bin zathan is depicted as
representations artistic benzite then
okay let's see how the Japanese depicted
so she is depicted as a goddess who
plays a string instrument like like the
Veena for instance we have and she's on
a dragon here
here again she's playing a wind a string
instrument
here uh sometimes she's not Dragon
Sometimes some other Beast sometimes on
a Lotus over here she's on a on a swan
like uh in India let's see this over
here she's on a White Lotus like the way
she's depicted in India so yes
benziathan is clearly the Japanese
version of Saraswati and she is even in
Japan the goddess of knowledge and
wisdom and literature and femininity and
and water she is strongly associated
with water in the sea sometimes she is
shown as being on a fish Sometimes some
other animal
here it's a dragon and so on yeah and
she always has a string instrument with
her so it's clear that anahita is the
portion Saraswati and benzitan is the
Japanese Saraswati do you know the
distance between Persia and Japan all of
that was indianized at one point in time
and yeah that's the history
right what else shall we talk about
rajit says our history textbooks say
that before the European colonization of
Africa there was nothing but jungle and
dangerous wild animals and
primitive backward uncivilized people in
Africa is this another propaganda to
make the Europeans look Superior no it's
propaganda designed to hide the fact
that Europe destroyed Africa
Africa was an extremely developed place
it had its own beautiful cultures it had
kingdoms and Empires and civilizations
yeah take a look at Africa how large it
is
and Europe reduced this to complete
abject misery and poverty and to hide
that they have depicted Africa like this
so let's talk about some of the African
kingdoms we know about Egypt Egypt is
well over here
and India had ancient ties with Egypt we
know that so Egypt uh everybody knows
about that we also know about some of us
may know about Carthage which was in
North Africa Tunisia yeah the Empire of
Carthage from the 9th century BC to
about the second century BC which was
eventually destroyed by the Romans again
Europeans then you heard the Kingdom of
Aksum in Ethiopia Eritrea that region
from the first century BC to the 8th
Century BC or thereabouts uh wonderful
very Advanced Kingdom with a beautiful
culture you had us in Sudan
if you go to Sudan you had the kingdom
of kush
from I don't know eight ninth Century BC
to about the fourth Century A.D you had
uh the Ghana Empire
in Western Africa in in Mauritania and
Mali very rich very prosperous Empire
from the 5th Century 82 about the
I don't know 12 13 14th Century A.D you
had the Mali Empire also we know about
Mansa Musa and all that yeah we had a
kingdom of the Great Zimbabwe in
southern Africa which had a Monumental
architecture and palaces and fortresses
and all that we had the kingdom of Benin
which was destroyed which which was from
the 13th century until
1897 when it was destroyed burned To The
Ground by British troops
so Africa had wonderful history a very
ancient and Rich
history and beautiful cultures the
Africans are not one single people
there are so many different ethnicities
and and cultures within Africa and today
it's like you know Africa the Africans
are just one people and there was
nothing in Africa except uh
jungles and poverty and savagery that's
not the case it is Europe that is
totally destroyed Africa totally
destroyed Africa
so yeah that's the thing about Africa
whatever propaganda has been put in
place has been put in place by the
Europeans to kind of hide what they have
done to Africa
okay next question
foreign
says what's the difference between
happiness joy and Bliss
we're talking philosophy here philosophy
so listen I don't uh
who am I to teach you what is joy
happiness and peace let us go to our
ancient scriptures shall we let us go to
the theater upanishad and let's talk
about Bliss and joy and happiness
upanishad first let's put that on the
screen
is it on the screen
foreign
so these are available in
Sanskrit they are available in Tamil
they're available in Telugu
they're also available in the Roman
script in English yeah so let's talk
about the Anand Valli which is the
second chapter of the thetriya upanishad
and let's go to a translation now these
translations are not necessarily very
accurate but I'm just putting on the
screen so that we get an idea of what
what it talks about so it's a it's a
we're going to talk about this
particular anuvaga eight of the
anandabali okay
uh so it says suppose a youth a young
person a good youth learned in the
sacred lore promptest in action
steadiest in heart strongest in body
suppose he owns the entirety of the
Earth with all of its wealth that is one
human Bliss
what is a hundred times the human Bliss
that is one Bliss of the gandhar was the
human ganderbas
what is a hundred times the Bliss of
human ganderwas that is one Bliss of the
Deva gandharmas
what is a hundred times the place of the
Deva Gander was is one Bliss of the
pitrus
the pitrus
uh what is a hundred times the Bliss of
uh is one Bliss of the they was born in
ajana karma Devas
and 100 times the Bliss of the also of
the these Devas is one place of the
karma Devas who have reached Deva look
by work
then 100 times that is
uh the place of the karma Devas is one
Bliss of the Devas of the Deva look
there are 33 Devas eight vayu's eleven
rudras twelve adityas Indra and
prajapati these are the main Devas a
hundred times the Bliss of the main
Devas is one Bliss of Indra who is the
Lord of all the Devas the king of the
Devas a hundred times the Bliss of Indra
is one Bliss of brahaspati the teacher
of Indra a hundred times the place of
brahaspati is one Bliss of prajapati the
Lord of all the creatures
and a hundred times the blitz of
prajapati is one Bliss of Brahma Lord
Brahma and Brahma embodies the entire
Bliss of the universe so our Bliss is
part of the Bliss the the collective
Universal Bliss of Brahma so that is
something you get to that that the
so our ancestors our ancients had really
thought about these things in extremely
a great depth and detail so that's what
I can offer you about happiness joy
bliss all that yeah
so yeah that's about that okay we are
almost at the end of uh today's session
let's take a couple more questions I
have so many more questions I'm gonna
have to not take them all
let's take one two more and then I'll
take some from the live chat Muhammad
yakub Khan says in Taiwan many
pakistanis have opened restaurants in
the name of India
Indian restaurants yeah and we have to
point out many times to our Indian
Embassy but still they are not we are
not finding a permanent solution
listen in India there's nothing you can
do about this if Pakistan is open Indian
restaurants well their Cuisine is also
Indian Cuisine and they're gonna try and
cash on the name of India to get
customers and they'll say yes we're
Indians whatever the thing is this
in India in every small town big city
you have
tens of thousands of Chinese restaurants
run by Indians so do we want the Chinese
to protest so these things there's
nothing you can do about it even if we
protest to the Indian Embassy the Indian
Embassy is not in a position to force
the pakistanis to say these are not
Indian restaurants these are Pakistani
restaurants because there is no such
thing as Pakistani Cuisine even
Pakistani Cuisine is Indian Cuisine even
Bangladeshi Cuisine is Indian Cuisine
yeah that's what it is that's what it is
so yeah in a way we should
well if you want to you can take it as a
compliment that everybody wants to be
Indian yeah uh one hears that when
pakistanis travel out of India they
pretend to be Indians so that people are
not scared of them you know so
yeah that's the that's the thing or
India
Daniel Nicholson says is it possible to
actually develop cruise missiles with
literal sea skimming capabilities as
shown in Sci-Fi movies like stealth
where the ucav displayed such
capabilities if so how would such
missiles maneuver amongst ground
structures
so it is certainly possible to develop
such missiles you could have subsonic
missiles supersonic missiles which is up
to 6000 kilometers per hour or
hypersonics which are from six to twelve
thousand kilometers per hour
high hypersonics are up to 30 000
kilometers per hour and then you have
re-entry speeds which are higher than 30
000 kilometers per hour so let's say you
want to develop a Hypersonic missile uh
which is based on RAM scramjet
technology it is possible to uh
to give it to see skimming abilities
when it's on over C it can like be about
10 meters or maybe five meters above the
surface as long as the waves are not too
high it will do fine but when it uh so
let's
let's let's take a hypothetical scenario
and don't get angry okay I'm just it's
just a hypothetical scenario uh let's go
to the map
let's take this completely hypothetical
scenario let nobody get offended that
you have a submarine
in let's say the Indian Ocean
and it has a Hypersonic missile with sea
skimming ability capabilities then you
want to
make this missile pay a visit to London
let's say okay this is just a game this
is entirely hypothetical nothing no hard
feelings here but let's say we want our
missile to play pay a visit to London so
you would launch the missile let's say
from from the submarine and it will go
over the sea
and you want it to fly let's say 10 5
meters above the sea or let's say 10
meters so that it doesn't hit any ship
and uh you can uh make the the missile
talk to your satellites overhead so that
you know where the ships are and all
that and mostly nobody has any radar
over the over the ocean
so it's fine nobody will be able to
detect it especially when it's traveling
at Hypersonic velocities then maybe you
wanted to travel over land where there
are very few habitations so you know in
desert areas and all that
maybe Somalia the Horn of Africa
Djibouti Eritrea All Desert uh Sudan
Egypt Libya mostly desert and you can
plot the exact coordinates of the exact
precise path you wanted to travel in in
the missiles computer system in the in
the microchip and all that so it can
take a past path of least resistance and
then it can very quickly cross France or
whatever go over the sea and then reach
London overseas all so you can certainly
program this if you if you are able to
give the missile a sufficient
maneuverable maneuvering capabilities
and you have such technology which
already exists
so I'm not sure if any missile has been
announced that is a Hypersonic missile
and it also has sea skimming
capabilities but it's certainly within
the realm of possibility given the
present technology that's already
available among the major nations of the
world
uh when it comes to ground structures
you would want the missile to stay a
little higher so you can program the
exact coordinates of the path you wanted
to travel based on where you know there
are not too many ground structures
mainly over deserts and forests and all
that you can make it travel fly at maybe
10 meters maybe 10 20 meters maximum so
that nobody can detect it on radar from
far that sort of thing so it's certainly
possible
all right I think we will uh I will not
be able to take all the other questions
I have selected let's now take some
questions from the live chat my dear
friends if you have questions you would
like me to ask right now on the live
chat go for it and I will take some
question
from the live chat
samarth says why are people generally
attracted towards white skin tone
historically Indians had did not have
any such thing it's only in the past
in in the past Millennium when we were
you know occupied by foreigners that
this sort of attitude seems to have come
in look at the ancient uh paintings in
ajanta ellora ETC you see people very
attractive good-looking people who have
reasonably dark skin tone yeah
um think about Lord Krishna who's
supposed to be one of the most
good-looking men ever
he his name is Krishna he had dark skins
very dark skin yeah think about someone
like draupadi a very attractive lady
from the past she also is known to have
had dark skin so it's not like it's
always been like that this is these are
attitudes that have crept into Indian
Society along with other defects in the
past 1000 years
when a society is under foreign
occupation it is enabled it is prevented
from functioning the way it naturally
functions and and it's under
a lot of stress external stress and
that's why all these defects creep into
society
and that's one of the things is this
supposed attraction towards white skin
tone
all right let's see something else do we
have another other questions
says what characteristics should I look
for in a potential future wife I'm gonna
get married but I'm not sure what
characteristics and qualities to look
for in a wife well you should look for
somebody who's gonna be your friend in
the long run yeah obviously what someone
who is good looking attractive uh uh
maybe good family and all that yeah but
marriage is a long-term thing hopefully
it's a lifelong thing so you want to be
with somebody who is going to be a
friend for you in the long run and
somebody who's going to be able to
support you
and and and uh encourage you and all
that through thick and thin so that's
what you need to learn no need to look
for
today everybody is like especially the
the younger Generations it's like let's
try a few relationships and see how it
goes and I'm sure I can do better and I
want to find my dream soul mate or
something there is no such thing as a
dream Soul made or any such thing find
somebody with whom you can spend the
rest of your life it doesn't have to be
what so what what the movies show as
some kind of star-struct lovers or or
soul mates or any such thing it should
be somebody with whom you can be very
comfortable and somebody who's gonna
support you so if you find somebody like
that it's obviously it means that you're
lucky but yeah
this currently there's a attitude let's
have like 10 15 relationships let's have
a few breakups and we will learn along
the way
if you have this attitude that I'm gonna
eventually find the right person you're
never gonna find the right person
because you even if you find so what
could be the right person you'll always
feel that yeah there could be some
somebody better waiting for me so you
know historically these this role of
finding a right partner used to be left
to the elders to the parents to the
family today it's all broken down
because of the breakup of the extended
family system so yeah today we have this
this uh this going on in society and
it's it's causing problems yeah
so the characteristics you want to look
for firstly understand marriage is
supposed to be hopefully a lifelong
thing yeah
so look for somebody with whom you can
be really comfortable somebody who will
really support you and somebody who is
genuinely a friend
a friend
that's that's ideally what you want and
obviously that person should be you know
good looking and all that that's also a
good quality to to have I I suppose
uh okay shall we take maybe a couple
more questions
is struggling with complex numbers
complex numbers it's it's a it's a
beautiful field in mathematics yeah
obviously it's it's definitely something
that some people would struggle with I
would say most people would struggle
with so you have to go back to the
basics start with the very basics of
what a complex number is yeah
a plus IB or X Plus i y or whatever yeah
uh and start with the very Basics and
practice practice you wanna you wanna
Master mathematics any branch or field
of mathematics you have to solve
hundreds maybe thousands of problems and
the more problems you solve the more
comfortable you get with it so if you're
struggling at a certain level you have
to go back to a couple of levels before
this because if you're struggling here
mathematics is like a building first
floor second floor third floor fourth
floor ground floor so if you're
struggling at the fourth floor maybe the
problem is with your fundamentals at
floor number two or floor number one or
maybe at the ground floor itself so go
back revisit those Concepts master that
then progress forward that's how it is
done that's the logical process of
mastering mathematics at the end of the
day it's a lot of practice practice
I think anybody can Master mathematics
especially Indians Indians have
historically genetically been really
good at math we have produced the best
mathematicians historically so yeah all
the best sir
right what else do we have
um
uh Tejas says did the Greeks ever
conquer patliputra it is said that the
Greeks once reached patliputra maybe in
the aftermath of the dissolution of the
shunga Empire because the shunga empire
was started by it was founded by push
about the great senapati of the last
modern Empire Emperor by assassinating
the emperor during America parade and it
was I think brihadrita who was the last
mauryan emperor and he was married to a
Greek Lady an Indo Greek lady and I
forget the name of her father he was one
of the kings in in Gandara in one of the
indo-greek kingdoms yeah
uh Demetrius was it I I don't quote me
on that
so uh
assassinates
the last Maori Emperor he makes
the mauryan impresses Empress of Widow
her father is a king in gandhar so he
takes the opportunity to come and come
to his daughter's rescue because it
gives him a viable cause to go to war
and when there is
chaos
when the emperor has been assassinated
and a new guy is trying to establish
power it's always a good opportunity for
an outsider to come in and you know try
to conquer territory bite away territory
so it is believed that the Greeks did
reach partly Putra so some accounts do
say that I I do recollect reading some
of them it was not a long-lived
phenomenon eventually we know that the
shungas did establish a strong Empire
yeah but initially the Greeks may have
reached
and maybe even in the future after the
Empire
dissolved maybe possibly the Greeks
maybe once could have come up to partly
Putra even a Miranda the great dharmik
Buddhist King Melinda he also tried to
move into patliputra he he marched
eastwards and he was eventually stopped
and defeated by the great king karavela
of Kalinga
so yeah very interesting history yeah
very interesting and this is this is
something nobody bothers to teach you in
in in the Indian education system
um
uh what else do we have let's take one
more question somewhere
okay did porus defeat Alexander the the
Greek most likely poros defeated
Alexander the Greek the Greeks will
obviously say that Alexander was great
but he was made to
turn back with his tail between between
his legs and go back to Babylon where he
died of the injuries and wounds he had
earned during the attempted invasion of
India yeah so most likely I mean the the
Russian Admiral jokov one of the great
Admirals of offer of the USSR wrote
about this and he said that the
Alexander's invasion of India attempt to
in where India most likely ended in
defeat at the hands of porus
whatever the name was yeah puru whatever
they call him the Greeks called him
porus so most likely it was a defeat of
course they they will never say it was a
defeat they will say that he defeated
porus and then he was magnanimous to him
he said that I'm gonna treat you like
one king treats another king and all
that but most likely it was a defeat at
the hands of Horus most likely
okay I think we're gonna end it over
here thank you so much for all these
questions always wonderfully exciting
interesting stimulating questions coming
in from all of you thank you so much for
that next weekend I am not gonna be able
to come live because I'm traveling I'm
gonna be in public cherry
but uh let's see if I can do something
from there possibly but yeah most likely
not but I'm gonna put up some clips and
all that so this channel we will keep on
rolling until the next weekend when I'm
gonna be back live and things will go
back to normal so until then take care
thank you so much and I will see you
soon thank you bye